this is Samaya
35246 the simile of the loot buus if for
any biku or bikuni desire or passion or
aversion or muddled or resistance in
regard toy cogn cognizable by the eye
arises they should re their mind in from
that this path is dangerous and
parentless thorny entangled it's a wrong
turn a bad path a harmful way this path
is frequented by untrue persons not by
true persons it's not worthy of you
therefore they should re in the mind
from those sights cognizable by the eye
if for any biku or bikuni desire or
passion or aversion or melness or
resistance in regard to Sounds
cognizable by the ear
um smells cognizable by the nose tastes
cognizable by the Tongue touches
cognizable by the body phenomena
cognizable by the mental faculty arises
they should re their mind in from that
this path is dangerous and perilous
thorny entangled it's a wrong turn a bad
path a harmful way this path is
frequented by untrue persons not by true
persons it's not worthy of you therefore
they should re in the mind from those
phenomena cogniz ible by the Mind
suppose the crops have ripened but the
caretaker is negligent if an ox fond of
crops invades the crops they'd indulge
themselves as much as they like in the
same way an unlearned ordinary person
failing to exercise restraint in regard
to the six fields of pressure indulges
themselves as much as they like and
falls into carelessness in regard to the
five strands of
sensuality suppose the crops have
ripened and the caretaker is diligent if
an ox fond of crops invades the crops
the caretaker would grab them firmly by
the muzzle they'd grab them above the
hump and hold them fast there then
they'd give them a good thrashing before
driving them away a second time and even
a third time the same thing might happen
as a result no matter how long they
stand or sit in a village or Wilderness
that Ox fond of crops would never invade
that crop again remembering the beating
they got earlier in the same way when
IU's mind is subdued well subdued in
regard to the six fields of pressure
becomes established internally it
settles unifies and becomes
composed suppose a king or their
Minister had never heard the sound of a
loot when he first hears the sound he'd
say my man what is making this sound so
arousing sensuous intoxicating
infatuating and captivating they'd say
to him that sir is a loot he'd say go my
man fetch me that loot so they'd fetch
it and say this sir is that loot who
sound is so arousing sensuous
intoxicating infatuating and captivating
he'd say I'd had enough of that loot
just fetch me the sound they'd say Sir
this loot is made of many components
assembled together which make a sound
when they're played that is it depends
on the body the skin the neck the head
the strings the pleum and a person to
play it properly that's how a loot is
made of many components assembled
together which make a sound when they're
played but he'd split that loot into 10
pieces or 100 pieces then Splinter it up
he'd burn the flinters with fire and
reduce them to ashes then he'd sweep
away the ashes in a strong wind or float
them away down a swift stream and he'd
say a poor thing indeed is this
so-called Loot and whatever else is
called a loot but people waste their
time with it careless and duped in the
same way aiku investigates form as far
as it goes feeling as far as it goes
perception as far as it goes activities
as far as they go and Consciousness as
far as it goes as he investigates them
in this way any ideas of I or mine or I
am do not occur to him so
him so
um this is a prime example of a practice
of su first and rasana
later colloquially
speaking because it's
often there's a there's a prevalent
notion that some of them rasana are two
separate things or two separate like
techniques let's say like two separate
types of meditation and
so um the SAS don't really support that
idea but to the extent that you could
argue that there is such a
difference it's exemplified by this sort
of practice where somebody's concerned
with directly abandoning as it says
their passion aversion and Metal
resistance desire essentially the five hindrances
desire essentially the five hindrances
in relation to the six senses and um
that's that's the samata aspect uh
calming down the filaments and then once
the mind is Cal as it says there uh
you're then in a position
to investigate more uh fundamental
aspects of your experience like the the
five aggregat
so in the suas it said sometimes like
some person might have a more of a
tendency for
Vias and then they should strive
to attain samata or they have more of a
tendency for samata and they should
strive to gain viasa to gain Insight not
it literally says that actually it says
gain which means it's a quality it's not
a technique or a method Sam is the
quality of Cal they pize the quality of
insight so they're not things you do mhm they
so they're not things you do mhm they
are qualities and
so um you can see that there's a very
big difference between this which is a
like it it clearly requires discernment
to some extent to to do this practice of
reflecting on the danger of um UNH
wholesome states which is incidentally
the only thing that the sutas Teach as a
method to abandon hindrances there isn't
a single mention of
absorption method that leads you to
samata the samata method of the sutas is
contemplating the danger in the in the
five hindrances and that occurs like
dozens of times then you have sutas like
these and you have sutas like those two
two types of thoughts majaya 19 which
are basically talking about the same
principle just in with like slightly
different terms like this one talking
about the six senses the other one talks
about three types of thought but
fundamentally all of it is about calming
the UNH wholesome States that's what you
calm because when you have just a
absorption or concentration practice
what you do is like you calm
everything it's like uh you imagine
imagine you have six
people um and three of them committed a
crime but you throw all of them in
jail that's basically what's happening
with with a contemporary idea of a Sumit
the practice you you don't actually want
to see what GRE diversion and delusion
is you just want to Cal everything yeah
so does that does that even qualify
because are these five hindrances on
that level yeah of course so the thing
is that that um attempt to to to just
come everything indiscriminately that's
also driven by greed a verion and
delusion ultimately so that's why then
the the states that result from that if
you read in between the lines you see
that there's still craving there because
there's mentions of like the lighting
the pleasure and and you know indulging
in the the the rap bodily Sensations
whatever in that precisely because that
effort that initial effort that would
have led to the right type of calm to to
actually discern what was UN wholesome
from the very start that that effort was
never made you
just people just took up a method and
then did it until this result came about
and there was no discernment of what
actually the five hces are and uh this
it does even say there there isn't like
I mean not that Janna is explicitly
samata but you could argue like sort of
um standard form of samata is is Jana
and S to say there is no jna without
wisdom and there is no wisdom without J
because it does talk about samata in
some other Su as as unification and as
composure so it's clearly moving in that
same direction and it said like even the
first first J if you don't understand
the danger in sensuality and you could
generalize it for any UNH wholesome
States you won't be able to attain it it
doesn't matter how much you can absorb
yourself because you can see that's that
sort of contemplation based on that
danger that you understood that's the
tool you're using like in all these
sudas to to calm the mind and then what
what comes from that is when the mind is
withdrawn from the
hindrances uh most classically described
in the the first J formula where it says
separated from un wholesome States then
you're in a position to to contemplate
these things because not because you
have like increased powers of of
observation of of like uh minute
perceptions that now arise due to your
absorption but quite the opposite it's
like you sort of looking at everything
from a helicopter now you can look at
you can survey the territory that's why
it says he examines form as far as form
goes it's not it so it's talking about a
generality of a broader picture not of a
not like you look at it through a
microscope and then you go back to your
normal State and what does that help you
with but if you if you look at
everything from above as it says
separated from these things then uh
eventually when you come out um when you
go back to your normal State and you're
like on the ground then you have you the
memory of like you know what you saw and
you know where to go and you will never
be able to get lost in that territory
whatever particularities then yeah so
then that's how practicing samata would
lead to permanent which is just the
temporary Liberation would lead to
permanent Liberation even when you don't
have this um
actual uh like bodily freedom and and
peace and so
on and then the narun wouldn't need to
practice zadi anymore as a to say it
would just be a pleasant for the sake of
a pleasant abiding but they don't need
to do it anymore if they don't want to
because they already saw became so
familiar with that territory from above
but having looked at it from above that
um that yeah they can navigate through
without ever uh inducing ignorance like
I said getting lost in like not knowing
where they are and doubt and so on mhm
mhm
yeah so are there any prerequisites for
getting the sumar right can we just can
can someone just out of the blue start
reflecting on the dangers of
sensuality like are there ways of doing
that wrong or can you never go wrong
contemplating the danger of sensuality
which basically means that your starting
point for the sonar would always be
right yeah so definitely it would be
better to do that than to do most things
people do but um of course it would not
be a genuine
human attempt of any kind if in your
daily life you haven't band sensuality
cuz like as it says the
prerequisite for the first J is he has
understood as it really is not just
intellectually or abstractly like you
know um these
things uh just an idea of oh these
things are not satisfactory or something
that everybody can have no he has
understood as it really is the danger in
these things
so you can ask yourself like yes I'm now
trying to practice meditation but in my
broader life do I still have a plan to
like go back to these things on a
physical and verbal level if the answer
is yes then you can be quite clear that
you don't see really that danger because
you would never want to go back to
something that's dangerous to yourself
so if you still want to go back is
because yeah you might have an abstract
idea of the danger but you haven't seen
it in that concrete sense that would um
induce that disenchantment that theas
talk about where like uh somebody tries
to throw you into this charcoal pits and
you just refuse in any in
any you would not consent to that so and
of course another thing is that um samas
is basically the the cultivation of the
seven factors of Enlightenment and or or
of Awakening and it said in the sutas
that these factors are acquired with the
Right View yes it's it's not uh that's uh I
View yes it's it's not uh that's uh I
thinka 4630 or something or 4730 no was
yeah no yeah not 46 the bo today yeah
with venerable it says he was
contemplating the it says like the
turning around of the five Aggregates
and then he finally he finally acquired
the seven factors of Enlightenment
meaning he like with the Right View
together with the Right View yeah so
that is actually
not so frequently talked about but just
as one gains stream entry or acquires
the noal path these seven factors of
Enlightenment or seven factors of
Awakening they are exactly on that same
level so it's just a full uh it's fully
synonymous seven factors of
Enlightenment with the noble AAL path
and then the Buddha in that Su also
confirms that like he says yes these are
indeed this these factors that you have
now acquired uh and if you then develop
them they will lead to full complete um
abandonment of of greed hatred and
delusion yeah yeah so it's um it's
because I mean the first one is is
mindfulness or sa recollection so um as
a s to say there cannot be right
recollection without Right View because
that's what you recollect you recollect
your understanding of what craving is
and based on that well you discern that
craving in the experience
dicha and see that's actually another
thing that sort of ties in with how um
Sam cannot happen without vasana like
D um you could say like distinguishing
or discernment of phenomena comes
before um uh joy and tranquility and
samadi and everything else because if
you cannot
distinguish in the most in the broadest
terms like what the problem actually is
in this
experience um then you will be calming
down the wrong thing like I said before
you you basically calming down like your
sense objects you not you don't see as i
s to said you you um the Assembly of the
cook that that discussion we previously
had about the sign of the mind yes you
don't see where that attitude or that
defilement is that you need to abandon
you just kind of go a roundabout way by
sort of destroying the whole thing and
then like that's that doesn't count
really because um it's it's
it's precisely because you become
accustomed to Discerning what Greer
verion and delusion is and you get that
confirmation that you did actually do it
properly out of the the piece that comes
from it that's how then your
understanding of what these greed div
verion illusion are becomes naturally
fortified but if you just get used to to
to just abolishing everything no matter
how peaceful it is you haven't really
like gained any understanding of how to
distinguish what what is Greed from non-
greed what is aversion from non aversion
it's also not really maintainable if you
continuously have to basically destroy
the whole experience which is impossible
in the sense as well yeah yeah so you're
just sort of replacing one thing with
another but why that in why that what
aspects were actually problematic you
you never really understood and um and
that's that's why and regarding the the
Thea component
it's um it said there that it's
examining like the it gives it simil of
the loot which is it doesn't mean that
you see some reality that's hidden it's
the same thing that you you had before
like it says that same loot but now you
see as it says there it's foundations
not like he he focuses closer on the on
the fabric of the of the loot like the
the word something it's it's a general
sort of thing that enables like it says
enables the sound and it because
initially you're just focused on the the
pleasant sound as it says there that's
gratifying that's pleasant but you don't
see what is the condition for this thing
to be able to be there yeah and that's
why then what you get to see with samadi
is
exactly you get to see the dependence of
everything that you could have gained
any gratification
or pleasure from you see that it's
dependent on this Foundation that's not
in your control and that's simultaneous
discernment it's not like a a sequence
that like so fast that you need to catch
it with this uh increased observation
cuz what how do you know that there
isn't an even faster sequence that
you're not seeing yeah that's endless
yeah so but this is like no you just see
the whole thing in in its
entirety and then anything that
you see anything that could possibly
arouse desire is within this like this
is the extent as far as it goes this is
what form is as far as it goes this is
what feeling is yeah so it doesn't leave
anything else yeah that contemplation is
done properly yeah I remember also the
Su in for it says if somebody has s but
he doesn't gain the viasa he should find
someone who can show him what is now
vasna and then he should ask that monk
like you know and then it talks
specifically about the conditionality of
of a vision phenomena how to examine
Saras it says yes so the vas there is as
you just mentioned entirely bound up
with seeing dependent origination which
is already which equals basically having
the Right View and I think it has
somewhere else as well like some not
pertain to true knowledge right so so
one this is something that one should
aim at establishing in one's experience
so we're basically saying that you know
to become a noble disciple is to gain
the foundation for doing both the Su and
the VAS widely if that right view is not
there then that's not quite the calm
that the sutas talk about when they talk
about Sam right and and definitely if
you did gain like a significant degree
of Sam like let's say the first Jan but
you don't have the right view that's a
red flag right there because um like as
this to say even a soop would hardly
have reached that point yet so that's
like you have an even even clearer less
defiled mind than
AAP like like the Buddha said um it's
like a pudle that has fish in it but
then it's mudded so you don't see
actually what's inside so like yours is
clearer than so's mind but you don't see
the fish clearly you don't see the four
noble truths you should really
reconsider whether that's actually the
right um so it's um and another s fact
says again feeding into how it's this
they're qualities they're not things you
do it says when you understand the sick
the eye the the sights you understand
eye pressure or eye contact you
understand the feeling born of eye
contact you understand eye Consciousness
and repeats the same for the the other
five senses then it says like the the starts
senses then it says like the the starts
to outline the entire path when you have
that um the for right drivings are
present the four uh bases of Power are
present the seven Enlightenment factors
are present the five faculties are
present and then it mentions Samana as
well it doesn't say that he does
sasana by like again him choosing MH
it's like these two things are there on
account of him having this understanding
beforehand of the six senses which is
another way of saying one of the many
ways of of pres presenting what the the
right view is understanding of the six
senses and um so really it's more like
um it's not even something you get to
choose it's more like some people could
could do the same
contemplation um and then they would be
more naturally inclining towards using
that contemplation to to um clear their
mind of the fs but they might not go far
enough to take it to the point of um
final final knowledge or final Insight
on the other hand some other people
might have a more of a tendency for that
um clarification and and Clarity of of
phenomena but they have a little bit too
much so then that results in
restlessness but it's the same
contemplation actually CU um it it
doesn't like if you contemplate the five
Aggregates it doesn't necessarily mean
that you you um you're going to be doing
the Bas you could do that also as a as a
way of calming down the mind you just
contemplate well look I'm having these
desires I'm having these pressures here
is this form actually mine this form
that I'm craving for or is this feeling
that I'm resisting is is it actually
mine like did I ask this thing to arise
uh and you contemplate any of the five
Aggregates but you only take it to the
point where
the the hindrances calm down and you
don't take it further so that's a person
who on account of what people would
generally think is repas is is inclining
more to towards samata because it's just
it's not even something like you would
be aware of uh yourself um necessarily
unless somebody else tells you or or
something like that it's it's just a a
natural inclination that each person
would have on account doing the same
practice of contemplation and
mindfulness which is the the thing that
binds everything together
yeah but now in that Su that we started
out with it says that by seeing the
danger in um you know greed delusion
melness and so on the Mind calms down
which is a su of the aspect perhaps you
can explore this a bit more now because
ordinarily one would assume thinking
about something which is dangerous would
make one Restless anxious maybe stir up
the mind and so there can be natural
tendency to not think about that which
is dangerous because you want to gain
calm now the Buddha comes along and says
the Mind calms down precisely when you
contemplate the danger in those
things so perhaps it's worth well
understanding why that is
so yeah I mean there's endless SS about
it how how that's what what leads to it
so um yeah so how how would you go about
because it it can sound to most people
like it's just a sort of abstract
philosophical Mantra like oh this is
dangerous this is d dangerous and
clearly that that won't do much so what
what is it that um how is it that you
contemplate the danger that say
mhm and what what does it mean when it
says there you Reign the mind
in away from these things does it mean
like you completely just delete them
from your awareness or is something more
to
that yeah let's go into that what does
it mean to re in the
mind like practically speaking Yeah from
from sense objects which is specifically
what is what it's talking about there so
where do you
go right because it's not that sense
objects disappear well can you decide to
make sense objects disappear that would
be almost like destroying your whole
experience well you can but the thing is
the Su is explicitly described in Jana
you walk sit lie down and it says it's
an Escape amidst the confinement of the
five senses you don't like stop the five
senses right so I'm thinking well you're
reeling the Mind back like it the fact
that it says mind
you have to bear in mind that mind is
not the kind of the thing you're looking
at it's not reel your attention back
like from looking at this thing out
there like okay I need to reel it back
pay attention to my nostrils it's the
mind which is already peripheral that's
what needs to be pulled back so that
theme that you're kind of operating in
that's kind of driving your
actions that is kind of too far out so
to speak and you need to bring that
theme back to something a bit closer
like the body for instance or the
feeling that you're acting out of
because that is well feeling is a good
example because like that is always
going to
be
like that's always going to be part of
the theme of what you're acting out on
so say your theme is just like total
sensual Indulgence for example that's
still kind of the background to that
background is the feeling still and it's
just a matter of kind of reing it back
to that
um as opposed to yeah yeah so can there
be an attitude of delight towards what
the senses present and at the same time
again in the mind would that be
possible or is that consideration well
things could be felt pleasantly but it's
different from Delight uhhuh this do
talk about it so by not welcoming and
Del lighting what the senses present
then at least the mind doesn't flow in
that direction say and there's also then
the opposite which is the aversion
wanting to resist it yeah so the
attitude of not welcoming and not
resisting um that is how the mind is not
moving along with what the sensus is
doing which seems to me which is the
raining and it doesn't need to go that
much further because otherwise you would
be if you go further than that you would
be again sort of reacting to what the
senses do right you go too far so that's
what have said you nether push forward
nor do you stand still yeah and and um
but then so what is it that's
dangerous is it the sense
objects yeah that's always good to
emphasize where is the actual danger
here
well since objects in of themselves will
be dangerous we will basically be lost
as as far as this practice goes so the
the danger is precisely in losing one's
mindfulness and when you lose it you
will just be by default acting out
that's the danger um but when that
mindfulness is Right which includes
which is not a mechanical technique but
which includes which is precisely the
recollection of the danger that's the
mindfulness which will prevent you from
acting out if you see a poison of snake
in the room you're not just gonna play
around with it because you put your life
at risk so you want to keep an eye on it
observe its movements where where where
is it but you don't want to come too
close nor do you want to forget about it
right so yeah so that's why the Buddha
said the six senses actually there was
this one suta where Mara comes to the
Buddha and says everything belongs to me
the eye the ear the nose um the tongue
the body the mind a Consciousness
belongs to me the five areas belong to
me everything belongs to me where will
you escape and um that's exactly the point
escape and um that's exactly the point
like if if your practice relies on just
G getting a different thing even if it's
just on the mental level you're still
resting on M's domain yeah and that's
not samata samata is even samata is like
you go outside of it temporarily of
course but um so so the the danger is
the the mental attitude that so the
problem is not that there's a trap there
the problem is that you are stepping on
it and um that's the the the whole point
of the first J where it says you
separate you basically separate from the
baits or separate from the traps not
that they're not there but you don't
bite them anymore and that's why it says
the five sensor senses are still there
but there is freedom within that there's
Freedom within that that which used to
be a trap and then further development
of samata is not like this in the
direction of okay now I absorb myself
it's the same contemplation of danger as
it do to say once you steud in the first
J you reflect on the Affliction in the
same way you reflect on the Affliction
of uh the the five hes and sity you
reflect on the Affliction on of the
first J which is now obviously not un
wholesome but it's just like Less
Pleasant than not even having that there
like the thinking in P yeah so you might
something beyond the first
J for example which would be the second
J yeah yeah so then then you you
wouldn't even need to predetermine or
know anything about what the second J is
you just develop the same principle in
relation to this uh thing that you have
now and then you would go further and
you just keep doing that and then as
just the say eventually you would reach
the sensation of perception and feeling
so you see even even to deepen the
samata you still need to contemplate and
they s to say that when when um
he says he reflects like this and then
his mind becomes established in that new
dimension quote unquote U because that's
what pulls the Mind back it's this
Clarity of this thing that's unwanted
and therefore the mind doesn't want
anything to do with it even though it's
still there
yeah and in another s the I already
mentioned the one that says walking
sitting standing during J but then
there's another one that says
uh uh if a monk is his his his
mindfulness is
is
imperturbable um his his effort is
unwavering his body is calm his mind is
composed while walking he set to be
diligent Ardent and Resolute so in other
words his body is calm while walking
which for most people would seem like a
contradiction because they they
associate the word samata which yes
could be translated as Stillness with
like Stillness of movement MH but
Stillness of movement is not the same as
calmness of mind or like like freedom
from defilements which is what matters
because I think I might have mentioned
that before like a sniper is very still
when he's about to shoot someone but
that doesn't mean yeah exactly but on
the level of the fance he's not actually
still so you cannot equate just lack of
so you cannot equate just lack of
movement with wholesomeness MH it's much
more subtle than that and that's why um
yeah you you you need to First
understand what needs to be calmed down
as it as it says you need to see the
signs of your mind because that's where
you see what the problem is and then you
can C down
yeah um um so from that discussion when
we started talking about the seeing the
danger it came across that it was just
simply seeing seeing the state of your mind
seeing seeing the state of your mind
which is the extent necessary you go too
far and try
to an example but
um that would be the middle
the middle ground if well as soon as you
start um bringing that State of Mind
into the focus that's TR trying to start
playing playing with it we've gone too
far um so is it just
then because it that that then reminds
me of of other practices I've heard of
just sort of just being aware of just
knowing that that is just the key but I
that doesn't seem right because that
could be misund yeah they what is
usually not emphasized in that is that
you have a responsibility for acting out
and that's where and that's where
hindrances are right it's not the
presence of a sensual thought or an
angry thought in and of itself that
constitutes a hindrance it's you going
towards it or wanting to move away from
it um so that's what needs to be
discerned and that's not that usually
doesn't get sufficient
it's not mentioned at all when when
people say you know like chur is
awareness and things like this yeah but
actually you are choosing and you cannot
not choose so you want to incorporate
that Dimension as well um
otherwise I I don't see how you can move
Beyond those hes yeah and also so first
of all maybe you could say to so just be
aware because he knows what that means
but the thing
is somebody who hasn't understood what
wholesome and un wholesome is their idea
of being aware might not be what they
actually need to be doing so then by
just mindlessly sticking to that they
would essentially omit the work that
they need to do to get the stream entry
because the S don't say you get to
stream entry by through
meditation uh you basically get to
stream entry by understanding how to
meditate um that's when the path begins
like you gain the seven enlightment
Factor so it's more like like um yeah to
some extent you will have
some uh your recognition of these mental
States will be
improving if you're practicing the
prerequisites of sensor strain virtue
and these things and and reflecting
honestly with the recognition that you
still don't see the full extent of it
and if at no point you become complacent
with thinking okay I understood now what
great div version and delusion are what
the hindrances are it's uncomfortable
but to keep the context that there's
still more to it there still has to be
more to it then at some point well you
will see the full extent of what UNH
wholesome things are and that's the
right View and uh as you said like um
putting it into making it into the
foreground when you're trying to discern
the mental state the thing is the mental
state can never be the foreground so
when we're talking about it
theoretically it sounds obvious like
sure there's the mental state and then
there's a sense object but practically
speaking there will always a tendency to
confuse the two like you think that the
way the sense object feels is the
attitude of the Mind towards
it and there's a line between those two
like because as the as the S say you
don't actually it talks about the five
senses in the first J and it says uh
amidst things sites cognizable by the
eye Sounds cognizable by the ear and so
on that are likable agreeable a pleasant
provocative of
lust there is an escape in the midst of
those things an opening amidst that
confinement so it's not even that you
change the way that sense objects
feel it other SS would say it's like um
you're dispassionate admidst that which
incites passion uh so you have to then realize
passion uh so you have to then realize
that um yeah that mental state is really
what needs to be the work isn't being
able to draw that line between that
which has it risen on its own which is
the sense object including the way it
feels because that that also belongs to
Mara as I should to say and then what
you're doing in regard to it and that's
why then as we always keep repeating it
starts with virtue because it's on that
same level of me when I
see uh something that I want to steal
with my hand and I do it see it's not my
fault that the thing present presented
itself as nice as something I would like
to have but it is my responsibility if I
go and take it so it's the same
principle on the mental level it's not
your choice at all whether the thing
presents itself as agreeable likable Etc
it's your choice when you take it up and
it's that taking up that you have to
recognize and it's that taking up that
you have to contemplate as dangerous not
the thing that came up cuz if like if
I'm not going to steal anything then I
mean you can present me like a case of a
briefcase of $2 million it's not
dangerous in itself it's dangerous when
I steal it and then I go to
jail but this has something to say for
also actively then contemplating the
consequences that would happen when you
do steal it then you get caught yes of
course the thing is you you you
contemplate the the danger and so on but
you always keep it at the back of your
mind that it's highly likely
that there's still more to that uh
mental state that you still haven't seen
so you don't assume like okay I see now
what the lust is and now it's just about
contemplating the danger you exercise
like um contemplating the danger but you
always keep in mind that you may not be
at any given time you can make the
mistake of falling back into
contemplating sense objects instead of
contemplating the mind so it's like as I
as I always give you example like um
somebody who's learning how to lift
weights um they don't just get focused
now on piling up the weight and lifting
as much as possible they always keep in
mind that as a
beginner they they can have bad form
like you can start uh making wrong
movements so not just about like
becoming complacent with okay this is
how you lift the weight and now just
doing it it's always watching out for
how you're doing it why you're doing it
and as as we always say like the
intentions behind your actions so
because you can be contemplating danger
out of essential reasons M because you
want some experience a release uh of
something like that and then you fail to
see that that is the hindrance like
you're contemplating danger because you
want something something because you might
something something because you might
want something more refined and
essential yeah yeah you want something
outside of this experience and that's
the actual thing that you should see is
dangerous so again like I said you fall
onto the level of sense objects or or
you could say sense experiences even the
more most subtle phenomena you're
craving for them and then you fail to
see is the craving in relation to them
that's the problem not like whether I
don't have this thing now that I think I
should have no it's like you get the
right experience which is the right C
and everything by not wanting and that
not wanting takes effort takes
discernment takes practice not it's not
just a choices awareness that you relax
into you need to understand what it
means to not want
things yeah so crave to understand how
not to Crave not crave for some
experience that you justify as wholesome
mhm and any experience that then comes
out of complete non-
craving is like you don't even need to
ask yourself whether this is wholesome
or or hear it from somebody else or you
don't even need to debate like which is
the right Jan which is not the right
Janna if there's no craving that's right
yeah that's how there's the craving that
bring about the ending of craving yeah
yeah of course that doesn't mean you
would have Janna uh craving inside like
samata is the coming of craving so it's
not that you have like craving Within
These when you succeed that's exactly
when I know but but Wellness to start
somewhere yeah yeah of course yeah just
clarifying because then you just see
exactly the same thing you you thinking
on the level of like what is the right
type of experience for me to have and
you don't consider that it doesn't
matter what experience it is what
matters is that there's no craving
that's what makes it whole yeah that's
perhaps good to emphasize that craving
does not necessarily need to be towards
this or that particular thing one can
crave experience itself yeah which is
also a form of craving yeah of course
that's why it says uh craving is that
which Delights here and there it doesn't
say it's something specific that like
this thing is craving and then if you're
not doing that specific thing then
you're free from craving yeah no it's
far more General than us
thein the all the
sixes and then you find the Escape
within that so that's why it's actually
a very very
lofty achievement to even reach samata
it's not like like
um you know everybody in the Buddhist
time was was already doing that and it's
just like
any uh within 5 days you get it or
something yeah or you do it yeah well
exactly you do a five day meditation
retweet and from day one people instruct
you suas that's actually seriously
suas that's actually seriously
misleading yeah so to say the way to the
deathless is Su mhm and then the next
the way to the death list be B
yeah yeah so you
so you
could cve for understanding if if that's
synonymous with the ending of
CRA yeah if you if you keep in mind that
like see the the the issue with this
idea of craving or the end of craving is
that uh you shouldn't
confuse like you will have a general
sort of desire to understand
and you don't give that up but you don't
justify like acting out of
restlessness and doubt and like no you
see yes I I have this General Chanda as
to say like um interest in understanding
but you don't
justify all sorts of other UNH wholesome
States and in the name of you know
craving for the end of
craving so
um because then that's more like just
replacing one hindrance with the
other yeah if you
imagining if you're if you're if you
have some picture of what this
understanding will look like and your
experience and you're creating after
that that's yeah you you you you if you're
that's yeah you you you you if you're
thinking again in terms of like some
experience that I want to
get no you you should think of it more
is is in how how do I clarify non-
craving in regard to any experience and
then more you understand that the more
you it will make sense that actually it
kind of doesn't make sense to Cay for it
but initially you have to start with
what you have which is craving but the
more you understand it you see like it
is like niana isn't something that you
can crave for because it's it's not an
experience in in terms of like um
something that comes to you it's an
attitude in relation to whatever is
already there so if if you understand it
properly that's why it says the dhama
doesn't take time if you're thinking in
terms of like oh this thing I I will get
later sure you start with that but
eventually you realize like no if I had
understood this principle from day
one there wouldn't have been anything
stopping me from understanding what Iana
is it would then just be a question of
having a sufficiently strong mind to not
fall away from that Bas it's just that
basically nobody really starts with that
kind of strong mind so that's why it
takes time but the principle in itself
is timeless yes yeah that's it yeah
yeah that's why then you would have
people who would achieve arship in one
night others in two days others in seven
days other up to seven years uh because
it's just the the same principle but um
that is
timeless uh but um it's just a matter of
like how long it takes for the mind to
become settled in it so that it doesn't
fall away yeah but it's not that they
were like building up this nibana energy
or something it's just like uh
understanding it so that you don't fall
away from it even in the most um at
circumstances yeah the most pressuring
uh challenging circumstances that that
Clarity of that deathlessness not a
mystical state but the the understanding
of the absence of craving that doesn't
get perturbed
there's one Su I remember uh not you
know exactly but one Su says when the
when they experience a pleasant feeling
he experiences it detached but
experiencing a painful feeling he also
experiences it detached in PL more
painful the same so I guess that would
be that's same principle the principle
of samata yeah would be yes the
principle basically being detached
exactly yeah so so you experience all
feelings you experience and detached and
that's why it says well it's it's on the
basis of cultivating the force of the
poanas you get to that point where
you're detached from from these feelings
and then you can contemplate them uh
rightly as not yours before that you can
tell yourself that they're not yours but
fundamentally the mind is still un
unified with them yeah but can you be
detached from feeling and then not see
them as not yours that's basically say
the same thing yeah yeah so that's why
then um these Aesthetics in the in the
Buddhist time who did already have a
development of J which wasn't a common
thing but some of them did and then the
Buddha like B he just tell him one one
sentence and then he became an AR
because the principle is of not mindness
is already implied you just have to like
push it one centimeter further and then
that's it so um that's why it says a bik
who is some who is in samadi I think
that's in the first suas of the angaya
book of T it says he doesn't need to
wish may I see things as they really are
mhm like sometimes the commentaries
would describe that in order to gain
Insight from your samata you need to
like come out of the states and then
like the super methodical sort of a
process to it as if you do have to be
wishing for the insight to arise but to
say no whether you wish for it or
not um a mind who is composed sees
things as they really are yeah because
it's detach mhm as I said like seeing
things from that higher view like like
you're in a
helicopter you don't need to be uh
trying to uh you know make a connection
between that which you're seeing up
there and that what you're seeing down
there the the the connection is obvious
yeah and then also because you wouldn't
you wouldn't have reach that state of of
samata by accident like you you would
have gotten there always from the
starting position and having made effort
to to build up that Clarity of these un
wholesome States so the the connection
between that which you had before and
that which you now developed how you got
to it why it's beneficial all that
Clarity would be there so again there
cannot be um it cannot happen without
understanding MH it's like um like uh
you cannot accidentally do something
hundreds of times mhm if you didn't know
that it was beneficial yeah because and
especially because it doesn't give you
like an immediate result like
establishing the right context as it
says there contemplating that danger it
doesn't like give you like a you don't
get like a little sort of plus one
points or something you don't get a
medal yeah yeah it's it's just
uh that's why um like if you don't
actually that's what I said to say if
you don't have faith
you you will get carried away and uh you
won't be able to do the right thing the
necessary amount of times for you to get
the confirmation you your reasoning
which is affected with ignorance and so
on will take you astray at some
[Music] point maybe it's out of out of topic but
point maybe it's out of out of topic but
uh maybe you have some interesting
comment because I I read this letters of
sister V
[Music] so it basically tells that she basically
so it basically tells that she basically
attained
uh I think the stre and basically she
but then acted you know pretty deranged
like crazy and she
like that it's natural that she like
kind of stopped her interest in the like
particulars of the dama she stopped
messaging you know letters and so
on you mean it seems contradictory or
something maybe contradictory but just
you know can you comment on it in some
way that that it could be such a strong
experience that can be you know even
deranging like or well I wouldn't say
that she got deranged it it was more
like she was she already had these
Tendencies like you can you can see that
she um burnt the the letters and stuff and
um burnt the the letters and stuff and
she was already getting in trouble with
the other nuns and she had to live alone
like away from the other ones because
she was she she just couldn't get along
with the rest so it's like she was
already like that and then she was just
restraining these Tendencies out of the
restlessness of wanting to understand
the dhama and then once she understood
the dhama she felt like there was no
need to be restraining herself in that
way anymore so then she just basically
even disrobed um yeah so but then um I
mean that's his judgment that she got
The Right View at the end that's just a
that's that's just a sort of um
estimation but um yeah it's not
necessarily like
uh you you have also this case of this
sarakan in the sutas who was drinking
alcohol I mean she she she was still
keeping the eight precepts at least but
this guy was just even uh he was like an
alcoholic and and people were saying
like how can he be assault upon that and
then the Buddha said well if if somebody
can understand even something that was
properly said as properly said and
improperly said as improperly said if
this tree that if this tree that you see
here could understand that then I would
declare him to be a satap that doesn't
mean that soapa is easy of course it
just means that um well it's simple but
it's not easy it's like just being able
to tell what is dhama and what is not
dhama and then the fact that she wasn't
interested in understanding more it's
just because um like you could even see
that with the other day people in the
sutas who who um it's kind of
interesting like they would um they
would understand the dhama it would say
that the stainless eye of the dhama
would arise and you would expect usually
you know from the point of view of
somebody who still sees craving as
wholesome and doesn't see anything else
you would imagine oh but obviously like
why didn't he keep going
but then they would say just like uh
well you know I have I have a lot of
Duties to do so you mean is UN wholesome
yeah no no I'm saying like an ordinary
person basically who who who still
operates just from the point of view of
craving like left and right oh see they
they wouldn't be able to imagine how you
could like get the right view but then
not have craving to keep going or
something all right and then uh but they
would just say well Master Goa thank you
very much I just have many duties to
take care of and they would just go go
back and then keep the five precepts see
the monks every now and then give
offerings but not really be striving to
um uh go further because yeah it's it's
uh if it that's the one of the signs
that it is the real deal like you you
don't uh like oh that's what to say
actually it's like the seven grains of
sand compared to the to the great
mountain of suffering that's gone so
like I mean
yeah sure from the point of view of
anara it's it's not great but uh
especially initially uh you might not feel great a
initially uh you might not feel great a
great sense of urgency
to to get rid of those seven grains of
sand only like you know saruta and
molana who were super sort of
um already had such great faculties like
they they they had so much sense of
urgency that they just immediately okay
what's the Next Step what the next step
and within two two weeks they got toship
so yeah because if you fact know where
suffering ceases which is the
understanding of the for TRS you
basically know how to not suffer and
it's just steuding your mind further in
that understanding yeah and and that's
why also you you had to you saw the
Buddha often encouraging Noble disciples
he had to like tell them don't become
complacent because otherwise it wouldn't
quite make sense you would think like
noble disciple would be like this sort
of even more sort of uh energetic and
energetic and yeah yeah yeah I mean of
course they have understood what right
effort is so if they want to have it
they will have it but they don't
necessarily make the effort yeah exactly
yeah even monks like it would it would
um it would Ananda like Ana himself he
was just distracting himself with in
that in that case where they were in the
CA and they were just a wholesome
activity he just camping together you
know preparing the the robe for the the
Buddha robe for the Katina and then the
Buddha said like don't don't be
negligent devote yourself to the
practice so yeah I think there are there
are other SAS and I think more than more
than one there are a couple of SAS that
say uh these monks you know get
satisfied with
inferior discernments inferior
distinctions and you know they just stop
doing anything yeah because they got
this distinction they are satisfied yeah
yeah yeah from the point of view of of
yeah from the point of view of of
understanding craving everything else
has to be secondary because everything
else will be just an engagement with
some sense object so even if it's like
thinking about dhama well that can be
effective with craving so even that you
wouldn't think of as a as a necessary
you just see directly craving presence
of craving and ab of crav and then
everything else you see it as see
beforehand it would have been more like
uh I do these I do these things that I
think will result in Freedom from
craving but then the order flips you see
the freedom from craving directly and
everything you do is secondary to that
understanding to now Foster it and and
improve it so you you don't like hope
that these things will lead to fear from
craving anymore like d Tanga
practices like athetic aesthetic
practices you take them with this kind
of superstitious
uh view that I will do this and then it
will result in wholesome States for
Noble disciple is the other way around
he has a wholesome States and he sees
how these things can help that
further yeah which is actually ex
exactly the same because I mean if
someone eats another piece of cake is
because he believes that this piece of
cake will bring him some happiness or
some can Rel from his current feeling
which is exactly the same attitude as
someone that goes for like sitting eight
hours a day and believe that these
things will bring him some sort of
relief or determines to never lie down
this sort of thing like if again if you
do it with a with the right
determination you see the craving and
you see that this will help you not act
out of it then yes but if you just like
hope that by sticking to this for who
knows how many years craving will go
away by itself well the would have said
there can be no wearing away of
defilements without knowing and seeing
what those defilements are
and actually inas this dangas can
actually be hindrances because it says
the Wilderness DW gets ConEd you know
that I am a Wilderness DW another mon so
don't I
am I don't know eater at
one city you know and other don't do
that and he gets
ConEd yeah that's why then when de
wanted to make them compulsory he said
no let the ones who want to do it do it
and that would mean that those who see
can see the craving in their minds and
they see how this
helps then they could do it without a
without um any sense of external Duty or
conceit it's just a direct and then and
and see the important thing is then they
would see that they don't have to do it
that that would be the difference
whereas a person who's still uh clings
to to Virtue and Duty they would have
the sense of no no this is necessary and
then if like for some reason they cannot
do it because of some external
circumstance they would feel like
agitated and upset which you can see
even sometimes like when MKS I don't
know get sick and then they need to go
to the city or something and then they
have like this almost like sense of
exasperation because they cannot fulfill
the the the duty that they must be
always in the forest eating rough food
and and that sort of thing so
yesterday when we were sitting at the
table and then it came up that certain
people they don't have in discussion
maybe they don't they're not they don't
have the right priority if you remember
they not prioritizing the right thing so
there's they go astray or um they don't
take the understanding further um or
they misund
something um so the right priority would
be putting that craving first like
switch in that
order yeah ceasing to think that even
the views that you might have which
might have actually arrived from the
suas or or things like that ceasing to
assume that that just uh adhering to
that in of itself means that whatever
you're doing is good you start you you
start with those views uh because it's
necessary um um to to point you in the
right direction but at a certain point
you need to see that the purpose of
those views if they were correct is to
show you what craving is not to just
keep building up the view in and of
itself so you turn the questioning
around like the understanding that you
got of uh you
know the background of your mind and and
these states that you act out of now you
see that in relation to your practice of
thinking about mental stat stat and so
on you see that now that's a level where
you where you have to practice it like
am I acting out of doubt in relation to
the right things um but before that you
you certainly would have needed to to
some extent like replace your your wrong
views with just where wrong ideas with
right ideas but at a certain point it's
like about am I acting out of again yeah
craving in relation to the right thing
which makes it not right anymore
ironically
and the most important thing to
prioritize would be that sense of
uh always remembering that um there's
nothing that you can take for granted or
rest on as already right before the
Right View like you cannot assume
anything you cannot leave any any stone
unturned but what I need to prioritize I
don't know yeah exactly
so know I'm yeah so so but it's it's not
like a sense of
um yeah initially it feels like sort of
agonizing or or that it's some sort of
extreme view um that that that's just like as a
view um that that that's just like as a
safety mechanism just to be extra sure
but no it's it is that that is what
sense of urgency really is it's when you
recognize how deep ignorance really goes
and and that you cannot rely on any any
of the preconceived notions that you
have and you have to be willing to put
everything throw everything out um and
that's again way there cannot be
Y without faith as to say you will not
be able to go back far enough if you're
not willing to question everything even
what you think the Buddha said and what
you think the Buddha meant because see
even that you have not you do not have
access to what the Buddha actually meant
all you have is what you think the
Buddha meant
um so you you always um you always need
to to bear that in mind and then that
would prevent any kind of complacency
and you would see then that um he would
stop chasing after some specific Insight
you would just see like it's
about um just wearing a
um just wearing a
way that um
wearing away those Tendencies and then
uh there's nothing to expect like am I
wearing away the Tendencies or not
that's the question not like what will
happen at the end of it well what will
happen at the end of it is the
Tendencies will wear away that's it